Guide to the Robert B. Fisk Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Robert B. Fisk papers
1882-1929
WA MSS S-2683
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.34
(8 boxes)
The Robert B. Fisk Papers consist of family correspondence and business papers created and accumulated by Robert B. Fisk during the course of his career as an attorney and land developer in Potter County, South Dakota. Correspondence broadly documents nineteenth- and early twentieth-century South Dakota life, including the rapidly growing settler population, business and real estate transactions, politics and the transition to statehood, the conditions of workers and prisoners, and the effect of the Panics of 1893 and 1907 on the local population. Business records include correspondence from mortgage and wholesale companies for whom Fisk worked as a collections agent. Additionally, letters from family members document life in contemporary Kentucky.
Fisk, Robert B.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Carmen D. Valentino on the Arthur Corbitt Hoskins Memorial Fund, 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Business Papers, 1882-1929. II. Family Papers, 1885-1929.
Robert B. Fisk
Robert Brown Fisk was born in Covington, Kentucky in 1852. He was an attorney and land developer in Gettysburg, Potter County, South Dakota from 1884 until his death after 1929.
Scope and Contents
The Robert B. Fisk Papers consist of family correspondence and business papers created and accumulated by Robert B. Fisk during the course of his career as an attorney and land developer in Potter County, South Dakota. Correspondence broadly documents nineteenth- and early-twentieth-century South Dakota life, including the rapidly growing settler population, business and real estate transactions, politics and the transition to statehood, the conditions of workers and prisoners, and the effect of economic recessions on the local population. Additionally, letters from family members document life in contemporary Kentucky.
Frontier and pioneer life -- South Dakota; Lawyers -- South Dakota; Real property -- South Dakota; Dakota Territory -- Economic conditions; Dakota Territory -- Politics and government; Dakota Territory -- Social life and customs; Kentucky -- Social life and customs; Potter County (S.D.) -- Economic conditions; Potter County (S.D.) -- Politics and government; South Dakota -- Economic conditions; South Dakota -- Politics and government; South Dakota -- Social life and customs; Lawyers -- South Dakota; Fisk, Robert B.; Fisk family
- Business Papers, 1882-1929; Series I; 2.5; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  Business Papers consist of correspondence (chiefly incoming, though also including retained copies of some outgoing letters) and financial records (chiefly bills and statements). Correspondence includes letters from colleagues, clients, and prospective settlers, relating to legal matters and cases, to economic conditions in the Dakota Territory and South Dakota, and to real estate prospects and transactions. Of particular interest is correspondence from mortgage and wholesale companies (for whom Fisk worked as a collections agent) and from individuals seeking relief from debt, documenting the economic conditions in the Dakota Territory and South Dakota in the context of rapid settlement, widespread mortgages, and the Panics of 1893 and 1907.
  - Receipts, 1883, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Business correspondence, 1882-1894 (Box 1, Folder 2-13)
  - Business correspondence, 1895-1900 (Box 2, Folder 14-19)
  - Business correspondence, 1901-1906 (Box 3, Folder 20-25)
  - Business correspondence, 1908-1911 August (Box 4, Folder 26-30)
  - Business correspondence, 1911 September-1916 (Box 5, Folder 31-38)
  - Business correspondence, 1917-1926 (Box 6, Folder 39-50)
  - Unidentified notes and sketches, 1929, undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
- Family Papers, 1885-1929; Series II; 0.84; (2 boxes)
  Organized into two subseries: Correspondence and Estate Papers.
  Family correspondence addresses not only family matters such as health and welfare, personal financial situations, and births and deaths of family members, but also legal and economic topics related to the conditions in and prospects of the Dakota Territory and South Dakota. Estate papers document the holdings and distribution of the property of Fisk's parents, John F. and Elizabeth S.Fisk.
  - Correspondence
    Organized by sender and then arranged roughly chronologically.
    - Julia C. Fisk (wife), 1885-1898, undated (Box 7, Folder 52-53)
    - John F. Fisk (father), 1887-1903 (Box 7, Folder 54)
    - William Greene (brother?), 1887-1908 (Box 7, Folder 55)
    - Olin Meredith Fisk (son), 1893-1917, undated (Box 7, Folder 56-57)
    - John F. Fisk (brother), 1884-1911, undated (Box 7, Folder 58-59)
    - Charles H. Fisk (brother), 1901-1909 (Box 7, Folder 60-63)
    - Selene, (sister), 1898-1905 (Box 7, Folder 64)
    - Hennie (sister), 1896-1908, undated (Box 7, Folder 65)
    - J.W. Hale (brother-in-law), 1896-1899 (Box 7, Folder 66)
    - Otis Harrison Fisk (nephew), 1889-1901 (Box 7, Folder 67)
    - Ella (sister), 1895-1904 (Box 7, Folder 68)
    - Belle Fisk Andrews (sister), 1894-1916, undated (Box 7, Folder 69)
    - Elizabeth S. Fisk (mother), 1891-1904 (Box 7, Folder 70)
    - Nellie Michener (neice), 1897-1898 (Box 7, Folder 71)
    - Mary (sister), 1890-1891 (Box 7, Folder 72)
    - Tom (nephew), 1901-1904 (Box 8, Folder 73)
    - Gineva (cousin), 1902 (Box 8, Folder 74)
    - Sadie (neice), 1894-1899 (Box 8, Folder 75)
    - Other relatives, 1884-1917, undated (Box 8, Folder 76-78)
  - Estate Papers
    - Parents' estate documents, 1904-1906, undated (Box 8, Folder 79-82)
    - Estate correspondence, 1905-1929 (Box 8, Folder 83-84)